Finding Aid for James Oliver Curwood papers, 1897-1927
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James Oliver Curwood papers 1897-1927
Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927.
851315 Aa 2 UAm
Michigan based author of adventure stories set in Alaska and Canada, screen writer and motion picture executive, and conservationist, a founding member of Izaak Walton League and member of Michigan Conservation Commission. Papers documenting his literary, film and conservation activities include manuscripts of books, screenplays and other writing and correspondence and photographs.
14 microfilms
9 boxes
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 4 accessions: 1974 and 1977, by Mrs. Carlotta Curwood Tate (Donor No. 5549 ), daughter of James Oliver Curwood; 1994 by Ivan Conger
The collection is open for research.
The Curwood papers have been microfilmed with the exception of several printed. works. This finding aid provides both a reel list for the microfilm edition and a box list for the original papers. The Curwood papers were filmed by University Microfilms International in 1990.
The papers, 1897-1927, of James Oliver Curwood include correspondence; scrapbooks; and manuscripts of articles, books, and movie scenarios. The correspondence, arranged chronologically, deals primarily with three topics: that from 1897 to 1918 relates largely to Curwood's literary efforts; that from 1918 to 1921 concerns a mixture of literary and motion picture matters; and that from 1921 to 1927 focuses on conservation in Michigan.
Curwood, a contemporary and acquaintance of Zane Grey and Jack London, wrote adventure tales of the frozen north. His collection encompasses not only his major literary works, but also the numerous articles that he wrote for such magazines as Redbook, Cosmopolitan, Collier's, Munsey's, Outing, and Everybody's Magazine. During the second decade of this century, Curwood got involved in the infant motion picture industry, first as a writer for other companies and later as the head of James Oliver Curwood Productions. Consequently, his extensive correspondence with producers, directors, and business managers is quite revealing of the early development of movies.
In the 1920's, Curwood became deeply involved with the conservation movement, not only in Michigan, but throughout the mid-west. He was a charter member and active participant in the Izaak Walton League, as well as a prominent critic of the Michigan Department of Conservation under John Baird. In 1927, Governor Green recognized Curwood's efforts by naming him to the Conservation Commission. His correspondence during this period covers a wide range of topics including water pollution, forest fire prevention, sport fishery development, and increased protection for some of Michigan's dwindling wildlife, principally deer and partridge. There is also a great deal of information on the corruption of the Baird administration, particularly the political nature of warden appointments, lax enforcement and flagrant disregard of game laws, and the utilization of the Conservation Department to build up a Republican political machine in Michigan.
Correspondents in the collection include: Rube Babbitt, John Baird, Curtis Brown, Will H. Dilg, Russell Doubleday, Richard Fletcher, Andrew Glaspie, Fred Warren Green, David M. Hartford, Carl Hubbs, Harold C. Kinsey, Ray Long, Parish Lovejoy, Thomas Marston, Louis Mayer, Joseph Montrose, Charles Mott, Gifford Pinchot, Filibert Roth, Albert Stoll, Harold Titus, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Edward Voght, Henry Wallace, Russell Watson, Leigh Jarvis Young, and Frederic H. Zeigen. Note: other Curwood papers are located in the Indianapolis Public Library and the New York Public Library.
The James Oliver Curwood papers are arranged in thirteen series
Correspondence, 1899-1933
Miscellaneous Notes and Articles
Clippings
Manuscripts of Books
Manuscripts of Writings
Fragments of Writings
Movie Scenarios
Stenographers Notes, 1925-1927
Photographs
Miscellaneous Printed Items
Foreign Language Editions
"The Curwood Collector, 1972-1982"
Printed Works (not included in microfilm edition)
This finding aid provides a complete contents list for both the original papers and the microfilm edition of the Curwood papers.
The James Oliver Curwood papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, manuscripts of publications, copies of books, and miscellanea; include material concerning his literary activities, the writing and production of motion pictures, his promotion of conservation causes, especially forest fire prevention, deer herd management, and the campaign against water pollution, and his work with the Conservation Commission, particularly his disputes with the Michigan Department of Conservation, Governor Alexander J. Groesbeck, and state director of conservation, John Baird; also copies of correspondence collected by Ivan Conger.
Photographs include pictures taken on hunting and fishing trips to British Columbia, the Canadian Northwest, and other areas of Canada; portraits; and photos of the Saginaw River (Michigan), and of pollution caused by the Michigan Sugar Company; also one film (two videotape copies), including scenes from God's Country and the Law.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927.; Forest fires--Michigan.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Hunting.; Michigan. Dept. of Conservation.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Motion picture industry.; Owosso (Mich.); Water.
Contributors:
Babbitt, Rube S.; Baird, John, 1860-; Brown, Curtis.; Conger, Ivan.; Dilg, Will H.; Doubleday, Russell, 1872-1949.; Essanay Film Manufacturing Co.; Fletcher, Richard H.; Glaspie, Andrew Bird, 1876-; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Hartford, David M.; Hubbs, Carl L. (Carl Leavitt), 1894-1979.; Kinsey, Harold C.; Long, Ray, 1878-1935.; Lovejoy, Parrish Storrs, 1884-1942.; Marston, Thomas Frank, 1869-; Mayer, Louis B. (Louis Burt), 1885-1957.; Michigan. State Park Commission.; Montrose, Joseph.; Mott, Charles S., 1875-1973.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Roth, Filibert, 1858-1925.; Stoll, Albert, 1884-; Titus, Harold, 1888-1967.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Voght, Edward C.; Wallace, Henry Cantwell, 1866-1924.; Watson, Russell, 1891-; Young, Leigh Jarvis, 1883-1960.; Zeigen, Frederic H., 1874-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Videotapes.
Subjects - Visual materials:
Animals.; Camping.; Canada.; Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927.; Dogsleds.; Fishing--Canada.; Hunting--Canada.; Indians of North America--Domestic life.; Log cabins.; Lumber industry.; Michigan Sugar Company.; Pollution.; Saginaw River (Mich.); Women.
- Microfilm Edition
  - Correspondence and other papers
    - 1897-1906 (Reel 1)
    - 1907 (Reel 1)
    - 1908 (Reel 1)
    - 1909 (Reel 1)
    - January-June 1910 (Reel 1)
    - July-December 1910 (Reel 1)
    - 1911 (Reel 1)
    - 1912 (Reel 1)
    - January-June 1913 (Reel 1)
    - July-December 1913 (Reel 1)
    - January-May 1914 (Reel 1)
    - June-September 1914 (Reel 1)
    - October-December 1914 (Reel 1)
    - 1915 (Reel 1)
    - 1916-1917 (Reel 1)
    - January-June 1918 (Reel 1)
    - July-December 1918 (Reel 1)
    - January-April 1919 (Reel 1)
    - May-June 1919 (Reel 1)
    - July-October 1919 (Reel 1)
    - November-December 1919 (Reel 1)
    - January 1920 (Reel 1)
    - February 1920 (Reel 1)
    - March 1920 (Reel 1)
    - April 1920 (Reel 1)
    - May 1920 (Reel 1)
    - June 1920 (Reel 2)
    - July 1920 (Reel 2)
    - August-September 1920 (Reel 2)
    - October 1920 (Reel 2)
    - November-December 1920 (Reel 2)
    - January 1921 (Reel 2)
    - February-March 1921 (Reel 2)
    - April-May 1921 (Reel 2)
    - June-July 1921 (Reel 2)
    - August 1921 (Reel 2)
    - September 1921 (Reel 2)
    - October 1921 (Reel 2)
    - November 1921 (Reel 2)
    - December 1-15, 1921 (Reel 2)
    - December 16-31, 1921 (Reel 2)
    - January 1-15, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - January 16-30, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - February 1-15, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - February 16-27, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - March 1-15, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - March 16-31, 1922 (Reel 2)
    - April 1922 (Reel 2)
    - May-June 1922 (Reel 2)
    - July-August 1922 (Reel 2)
    - September 1922 (Reel 3)
    - October 1922 (Reel 3)
    - November 1922 (Reel 3)
    - December 1-15, 1922 (Reel 3)
    - December 16-31, 1922 (Reel 3)
    - January 1-15, 1923 (Reel 3)
    - January 16-31, 1923 (Reel 3)
    - February 1-15, 1923 (Reel 3)
    - February 16-28, 1923 (Reel 3)
    - March 1923 (Reel 3)
    - April 1923 (Reel 3)
    - May-July 1923 (Reel 3)
    - August-December 1923 (Reel 3)
    - 1924 (Reel 3)
    - 1925 (Reel 3)
    - January-June 1926 (Reel 3)
    - July 1926 (Reel 3)
    - August-September 1926 (Reel 3)
    - October-December 1926 (Reel 3)
    - January 1-15, 1927 (Reel 3)
    - January 16-31, 1927 (Reel 3)
    - February-March 1927 (Reel 4)
    - April-May 1927 (Reel 4)
    - June 1-20, 1927 (Reel 4)
    - June 21-30, 1927 (Reel 4)
    - July 1-15, 1927 (Reel 4)
    - July 16-31, 1927 (Reel 4)
    - August-October 1927 (Reel 4)
    - 1932-1933 (Reel 4)
    - Undated (Reel 4)
    - Correspondence with publisher, Bobbs-Merrill Co.
      - 1908-1909 (Reel 4)
      - 1910 (Reel 4)
      - 1911-1915 (Reel 4)
      - 1919-1920 (Reel 4)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Articles
    - Royalty statements and a contract (Reel 4)
    - Pen sketch, Curwood Castle (Reel 4)
    - Correspondence and clippings concerning bobbed hair 1926-1927 (Reel 4)
    - Conservation, memos (Reel 4)
    - Conservation, miscellaneous (Reel 4)
    - Depositions concerning corruption of game warden John Speck in 1919, 1921, 1922 (Reel 4)
    - Speech texts (Reel 4)
    - Research materials and article ideas, 7 folders (Reel 5)
    - Notes on Alaska, 2 folders (Reel 5)
    - Manuscript articles, 4 folders (Reel 5)
    - Printed articles, 4 folders (Reel 6)
  - Clippings
    - Biographical (Reel 6)
    - Conservation undated 1922 1926 and 1927 (Reel 6)
    - Scrapbook 1921-1927 (Reel 6)
      detailing Curwood's interest in conservation, particularly his political disputes with Governor Groesbeck and state director of conservation, John Baird
    - Literary
      - 1909-1909, 2 volumes (Reel 6)
      - Concerning The Honor of the Big Snows 1911 (Reel 6)
      - 1913 1925 (Reel 6)
      - Concerning The Wolf Hunters 1926 (Reel 6)
      - Concerning The Black Hunter 1926 (Reel 6)
    - Movie publicity (Reel 6)
  - Manuscripts of books
    - The Alaskan, 1923 (Reel 7)
    - The Ancient Highway, 1925 (Reel 7)
    - The Black Hunter, 1927 (Reel 7)
    - The Country Beyond (Reel 8)
      - Short story #1: "Peter - Just Dog", 2 drafts (Reel 8)
      - Short story #2: (Reel 8)
      - Short story #3: "Honor - and the Outlaw" (Reel 8)
      - Short story #7: (no title) (Reel 8)
      - Fragments of novel: chapters VI, VII, VIII, IX, XI, XIII, XVIII, XIX, XX, XXI, XXII, and XXIII (Reel 8)
    - The Courage of Captain Plum, 1908 (Reel 8)
      (originally Strang)
    - The Crippled Lady of Peribonka, 1929 (Reel 8)
    - The Flaming Forest, 1921 (Reel 8)
      (originally Strength of Men)
    - A Gentleman of Courage, 1924
      - Short story #1: "The Tragedy at Five Fingers" (Reel 8)
      - Short story #2: "Peter" (Reel 8)
      - Short story #3: "A Gentleman of Courage" (Reel 8)
      - Short story #4: "When the Gray Geese Race" (Reel 8)
      - Short story #5: "The Broken Man" or "Out of the Forest Shadows" two drafts) (Reel 8)
      - Short story #6: (untitled) (Reel 8)
      - Short story #7: "There Is a God!" (two drafts) (Reel 8)
      - Fragments of novel: chapters XIII, XIV, and XXII-end (Reel 8)
    - The Glory of Living (Reel 8)
      (autobiography published only in England, from which Son of the Forests,1930, was derived)
    - The Golden Snare, 1921 (Reel 9)
    - Nomads of the North, 1919 (Reel 9)
    - The Plains of Abraham, 1928
      - Curwood's notes (Reel 9)
      - First four chapters (Reel 9)
      - Entire novel (Reel 9)
    - The River's End, 1919 (Reel 9)
    - Swift Lightning, 1919 and 1926 (Reel 10)
      - Short story #1: "Swift Lightning" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #2: "The Hungry Horde" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #3: "The Hunger Madness" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #4: "A Message to his Master" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #5: "The Mating of Swift Lightning" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #6: "Swift Lightning Runs Alone" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #7: "The Deluge" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #8: "In the Lives of Beasts" (Reel 10)
      - Short story #9: "The Civilizing of Swift Lightning" (Reel 10)
      - Draft of novel (Reel 10)
    - The Valley of Silent Men, 1920 (Reel 10)
  - Manuscripts of writings
    - "l'Ange of Lac Brochet" (Reel 10)
    - "Peggy the Pirate" (Reel 10)
    - "The Red Sagamore's Hidden Treasure" (handwritten) (Reel 10)
    - "The Rebel Quintelle" or "The Ranger of the Florida Keys", 1894 (handwritten, with addenda) (Reel 10)
    - "Rocky Mountain Boys" or "The Skeleton Cave" (handwritten) (Reel 10)
    - "Senor Valentino - a Cuban Romance" (handwritten as a young boy) (Reel 10)
    - "Trail of Gold" (Reel 10)
  - Fragments of manuscripts
    - "Green Timber" (Reel 11)
    - "Isobel" (Reel 11)
    - Kazan, short story #6: "The Feud" (Reel 11)
    - Nomads of the North: "The Fight at Fort o'God" (Reel 11)
    - Miscellaneous fragments of stories, and political, autobiographical, and conservation writings (Reel 11)
  - Movie scenarios
    - The Big Adventure (Reel 11)
    - Get There Conniston (originally A Nice QuietTime) (two drafts) (Reel 11)
    - The Lady of Rugni (Reel 11)
    - Little Miss Tired-of-it-All (Reel 11)
    - The Little Yankee or The Under-Dog or The Sea- Breed or The Admiral's Daughter (adapted from the story The Admiral's Daughter) (Reel 11)
    - The Man of Vengeance (Reel 11)
    - A Matter of Ancestry or The Governor's Wife (Reel 11)
      (two drafts)
    - Nomads of the North, 1919
      - Memo from Curwood to Messrs. Carver, Hartford, Shipman, and Gardner October 8, 1919 (Reel 11)
      - Working synopsis written by Curwood (Reel 11)
        (two versions, two slightly different copies of each)
      - Animal action (Reel 11)
    - The River's End, 1919 (Reel 11)
    - The Unforgettable Crime (Reel 11)
      (with other titles also)
    - The Yellow-Back
      - Curwood's notes to accompany scenario (Reel 11)
      - Scenario (Reel 11)
      - Synopsis (Reel 11)
      - Story (Reel 11)
      - Copy of synopsis for David Hartford (Reel 11)
        (missing pages 45-70)
  - Stenographer's notes
    - 1925-1927, 10 pads (Reel 12)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (Reel 13)
    - Ethel Curwood (Reel 13)
    - Cabins, exteriors and interiors (Reel 13)
    - Camps (Reel 13)
    - Canoes and boats (Reel 13)
    - Catholic churches in Arctic, bishop on dogsled (Reel 13)
    - Farming and ranching (Reel 13)
    - Fishing (Reel 13)
    - Hunting and trapping (Reel 13)
    - Hunting trophies (Reel 13)
    - Indians (Reel 13)
    - Lumbering (Reel 13)
    - Mountains (Reel 13)
    - Movie stills (Reel 13)
    - Pack horses (Reel 13)
    - Saginaw River pollution (Reel 13)
    - Transportation, miscellaneous, including railroads and dogsleds (Reel 13)
    - Trip to Teddy Brown's (Reel 13)
    - Wildlife (Reel 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 13)
  - Miscellaneous printed items
    - Cutter, John C. Intermediate Anatomy, Physiology and Hygiene. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott Co., 1887 (Reel 13)
    - Harper's Fifth Reader: American Authors. New York: Harper & Brothers, 1889 (Reel 13)
    - Willson, Marcius. Outlines of History. New York: Ivison & Phinney, 1854 (Reel 13)
  - Foreign Language Editions
    - Grizli, 1964 (Reel 14)
    - Hrabar Dzentlmen, 1964 (Reel 14)
    - Kapetan Plum, 1964 (Reel 14)
    - Kazan, volcji pes, 1962 (Reel 14)
    - Kocovnici Severu, 1962 (Reel 14)
    - Kral sedych medvedu, 1967 (Reel 14)
    - Lutalice Sa Severa, 1965 (Reel 14)
    - Medvjedic Niva, 1967 (Reel 14)
    - Na Kraju Sveta, 1964 (Reel 14)
    - Nomades du Nord, Un Gentleman Courageux, La Piste du Bonheur, 1968 (Reel 14)
  - "The Curwood Collector", published and edited by Ivan Conger, Owosso, Michigan
    - Volume I, no. 1 1972 (Reel 14)
    - Volume I, no. 2 1972 (Reel 14)
    - Volume I, no. 3 1972 (Reel 14)
    - Volume II, no. 4 1973 (Reel 14)
    - Volume II, no. 1 1973 (Reel 14)
    - Volume II. no. 2 1973 (Reel 14)
    - Volume II, no. 3 1974 (Reel 14)
    - Volume II, no. 4 1973 (Reel 14)
    - Volume III, no. 1 1975 (Reel 14)
    - Volume III, no. 2 1975 (Reel 14)
    - Volume III, no. 3 1976 (Reel 14)
    - Volume III, no. 4 1977 (Reel 14)
    - Volume IV, no.1 and 2 May 1978 (Reel 14)
    - Volume IV, no. 3 and 4 May 1979 (Reel 14)
    - Volume IV, no. 1 March 1980 (Reel 14)
    - Volume V, no. 2 April 1980 (Reel 14)
    - Volume V, no. 3 and 4 February 1982 (Reel 14)
- Paper Originals
  - Correspondence and other papers
    - 1897-1906 (Box 1)
    - 1907 (Box 1)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1910 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911 (Box 1)
    - 1912 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1913 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1913 (Box 1)
    - January-May 1914 (Box 1)
    - June-September 1914 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1914 (Box 1)
    - 1915 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1918 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1918 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1919 (Box 1)
    - May-June 1919 (Box 1)
    - July-October 1919 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1919 (Box 1)
    - January 1920 (Box 1)
    - February 1920 (Box 1)
    - March 1920 (Box 1)
    - April 1920 (Box 1)
    - May 1920 (Box 1)
    - June 1920 (Box 1)
    - July 1920 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1920 (Box 1)
    - October 1920 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1920 (Box 1)
    - January 1921 (Box 1)
    - February-March 1921 (Box 1)
    - April-May 1921 (Box 1)
    - June-July 1921 (Box 1)
    - August 1921 (Box 1)
    - September 1921 (Box 1)
    - October 1921 (Box 1)
    - November 1921 (Box 1)
    - December 1-15, 1921 (Box 1)
    - December 16-31, 1921 (Box 1)
    - January 1-15, 1922 (Box 1)
    - January 16-30, 1922 (Box 1)
    - February 1-15, 1922 (Box 1)
    - February 16-27, 1922 (Box 1)
    - March 1-15, 1922 (Box 1)
    - March 16-31, 1922 (Box 1)
    - April 1922 (Box 1)
    - May-June 1922 (Box 1)
    - July-August 1922 (Box 1)
    - September 1922 (Box 1)
    - October 1922 (Box 1)
    - November 1922 (Box 2)
    - December 1-15, 1922 (Box 2)
    - December 16-31, 1922 (Box 2)
    - January 1-15, 1923 (Box 2)
    - January 16-31, 1923 (Box 2)
    - February 1-15, 1923 (Box 2)
    - February 16-28, 1923 (Box 2)
    - March 1923 (Box 2)
    - April 1923 (Box 2)
    - May-July 1923 (Box 2)
    - August-December 1923 (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - January-June 1926 (Box 2)
    - July 1926 (Box 2)
    - August-September 1926 (Box 2)
    - October-December 1926 (Box 2)
    - January 1-15, 1927 (Box 2)
    - January 16-31, 1927 (Box 2)
    - February-March 1927 (Box 2)
    - April-May 1927 (Box 2)
    - June 1-20, 1927 (Box 2)
    - June 21-30, 1927 (Box 2)
    - July 1-15, 1927 (Box 2)
    - July 16-31, 1927 (Box 2)
    - August-October 1927 (Box 2)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with publisher, Bobbs-Merrill Co.
      - 1908-1909 (Box 2)
      - 1910 (Box 2)
      - 1911-1915 (Box 2)
      - 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Garrett Reitberg, Grand Rapids baseball player 1924-1925 (Box 2)
      (from donor no. 4082
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Articles
    - Royalty statements and a contract (Box 2)
    - Pen sketch, Curwood Castle (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and clippings concerning bobbed hair 1926-1927 (Box 3)
    - Conservation, memos (Box 3)
    - Conservation, miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Depositions of 1921 and 1922 concerning corruption of game warden John Speck in 1919 (Box 3)
    - Speech texts (Box 3)
    - Research materials and article ideas, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Notes on Alaska, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Manuscript articles, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Printed articles, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Clippings
    - Biographical (Box 3)
    - Conservation undated 1922 1926 and 1927 (Box 3)
    - Literary
      - 1909-1909, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - Concerning The Honor of the Big Snows 1911 (Box 3)
      - 1913 1925 (Box 3)
      - Concerning The Wolf Hunters 1926 (Box 3)
      - Concerning The Black Hunter 1926 (Box 3)
    - Movie publicity (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook 1921-1927 (Volume AC)
  - Manuscripts of books
    - The Alaskan, 1923 (Box 4)
    - The Ancient Highway, 1925 (Box 4)
    - The Black Hunter, 1927 (Box 4)
    - The Country Beyond
      - Short story #1: "Peter - Just Dog" (2 drafts) (Box 4)
      - Short story #2: (last page only) (Box 4)
      - Short story #3: "Honor - and the Outlaw" (Box 4)
      - Short story #7: (no title) (Box 4)
      - Fragments of novel: chapters VI, VII, VIII, IX, XI, XIII, XVIII, XIX, XX, XXI, XXII, and XXIII (Box 4)
    - The Courage of Captain Plum, 1908 (Box 4)
    - The Crippled Lady of Peribonka, 1929 (Box 4)
    - The Flaming Forest, 1921 (Box 4)
    - A Gentleman of Courage, 1924
      - Short story #1: "The Tragedy at Five Fingers" (Box 4)
      - Short story #2: "Peter" (Box 4)
      - Short story #3: "A Gentleman of Courage" (Box 4)
      - Short story #4: "When the Gray Geese Race" (Box 4)
      - Short story #5: "The Broken Man" or "Out of the Forest Shadows" two drafts) (Box 4)
      - Short story #6: (untitled) (Box 4)
      - Short story #7: "There Is a God!" (two drafts) (Box 4)
      - Fragments of novel: chapters XIII, XIV, and XXII-end (Box 4)
    - The Glory of Living (Box 4)
      (autobiography published only in England, from which Son of the Forests, 1930, was derived)
    - The Golden Snare, 1921 (Box 4)
    - Nomads of the North, 1919 (Box 4)
    - The Plains of Abraham, 1928 (Box 5)
      - Curwood's notes (Box 5)
      - First four chapters (Box 5)
      - Entire novel (Box 5)
    - The River's End, 1919 (Box 5)
    - Swift Lightning, 1919 and 1926
      - Short story #1: "Swift Lightning" (Box 5)
      - Short story #2: "The Hungry Horde" (Box 5)
      - Short story #3: "The Hunger Madness" (Box 5)
      - Short story #4: "A Message to his Master" (Box 5)
      - Short story #5: "The Mating of Swift Lightning" (Box 5)
      - Short story #6: "Swift Lightning Runs Alone" (Box 5)
      - Short story #7: "The Deluge" (Box 5)
      - Short story #8: "In the Lives of Beasts" (Box 5)
      - Short story #9: "The Civilizing of Swift (Box 5)
      - Lightning" (Box 5)
      - Draft of novel (Box 5)
    - The Valley of Silent Men, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts of writings
    - "l'Ange of Lac Brochet" (Box 5)
    - "Peggy the Pirate" (Box 5)
    - "The Red Sagamore's Hidden Treasure" (handwritten) (Box 5)
    - "The Rebel Quintelle" or "The Ranger of the Florida Keys", 1894 (handwritten, with addenda) (Box 5)
    - "Rocky Mountain Boys" or "The Skeleton Cave"(handwritten) (Box 5)
    - "Senor Valentino - a Cuban Romance" (handwritten as a young boy) (Box 5)
    - "Trail of Gold" (Box 5)
  - Fragments of manuscripts
    - "Green Timber" (Box 5)
    - "Isobel" (Box 5)
    - Kazan, short story #6: "The Feud" (Box 5)
    - Nomads of the North: "The Fight at Fort o'God" (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous fragments of stories, and political, autobiographical, and conservation writings (Box 5)
  - Movie scenarios
    - The Big Adventure (Box 5)
    - Get There Conniston (originally A Nice QuietTime), 2 drafts (Box 5)
    - The Lady of Rugni (Box 5)
    - Little Miss Tired-of-it-Al (Box 5)
    - The Little Yankee or The Under-Dog or The Sea- Breed or The Admiral's Daughter (adapted from the story The Admiral's Daughter) (Box 5)